Among the freshly blooming dandelions
And the droplets of water which couldn't quite become snow
I thought I could make out a face stained with tears
So I offered my umbrella without a second thought
Is going left or right correct?
The path ended before I could really decide
But surely the right call is the one which spares that special someone
From any painful experiences
So with a little courage, take that plunge forward
If everything's all crooked, take an oblique path
As long as you're moving forward, you'll find the light
Like those little birds that huddle together and cry out in unison
We'll definitely ring in the start of a new season
And so spring will embrace us once more
We'll splash paint on some new pages
We became fast friends, we enjoyed some good food
We might've even argued a little
But we carry those little moments in our hearts
As reasons which compel us toward a future that can't possibly be mistaken
No matter how many times we find ourselves lost among sunlit trees
Today has been carried here by the winds on a one-way ticket
That blooms into a perfect day
Being Here
（あかり）
じゃ 試作ということで…
So let's do an experiment.
Finest Quality
Refined Rice Flour
Domestic
100% Paddy-grown
Glutinous Rice
（あかり）とりあえず 200グラムで
作ってみようか 白玉だんご
Should we start with 200 grams for the sticky rice flour dumplings?
Yeah!
Nod
（ひなた）
名前は“冷やし白玉シロップ”で
いいかな？
Should we call it "chilled rice flour dumpling with syrup"?
Yeah, that's really cute!
（あかり）うん！　かわいい 絶対
（ひなた）毎年恒例の
夏の商店街のお祭りに—
Crescent Moon was going to have a food stand at
the annual summer festival in the shopping district.
三日月堂(みかづきどう)も屋台を出すことになり
March City Shopping District
March City Festival
Sunday, July 28th
今年は
おじいちゃんが 私たちに—
This year, Grandpa let us decide what would be on the menu.
メニューを
任せてくれることになりました
白玉だんごの作り方は
簡単に言うと…
To explain it simply,
you make rice flour dumplings like this.
Knead the rice flour in cold water
Step one: knead the rice flour in cold water.
Roll into balls and boil in hot water
Step two: roll into balls and boil in hot water.
That's all!
Giggle
Ahaha
Knead the rice
flour in cold water
Roll into balls and
boil in hot water
That's all!
ウフフッ…　ねっ？　簡単でしょう
Giggle
Ahaha
See? Simple, right?
Giggle
Ahaha
Knead the rice
flour in cold water
Roll into balls and
boil in hot water
That's all!
Ahaha
What?
Giggle
Ahaha
えっ！　“簡単でしょう”って
ホントに簡単すぎる…
"Simple, right?"
Giggle
Ahaha
Knead the rice
flour in cold water
Ahaha
Giggle
Knead the rice
flour in cold water
Giggle
Ahaha
It's way too simple!
Knead the rice
flour in cold water
What?
Ahaha
Giggle
What?
Ahaha
Giggle
（あかり）白玉粉200グラムに
お水は大体160ccくらいかな
I think we'll go with 200 grams of rice flour and about 160 cc of cold water.
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
Rice flour is
sold at the
supermarket
ボウルに粉を入れて 水を
ちょっとずつ入れて混ぜていきます
Put the flour in a bowl and pour the water in a little at a time, mixing as we go.
なじんできたら
力を入れて ギュッギュと練ります
Once it's mixed well, put some muscle into it as you knead.
If you put in too much water,
it'll get sticky and make it hard to form into balls,
水は 入れ過ぎると
ベタベタして丸めづらくなるから
生地が まとまるくらいで
ストップね
so stop when the dough has taken shape.
それを手でコロコロ 棒状にして…
Then roll the dough out into rod shapes with your hands
ひと口サイズに指でちぎって…
and rip them apart into bite-sized pieces.
うん つかめてきた コツが
I'm getting the hang of it!
Knead
Roll
楽しいね これ
This is fun!
Rice flour dumplings!
おだんご！　これ モモの！
This one's mine!
Fwhaaa
Push
Squish
Yes, you're doing good, Momo.
All mine!
（あかり）うん モモ 上手ね
でも ちょっと大きいかな
But maybe it's a little big.
（ひなた）
お姉ちゃん　こんくらいかな？
Sis, about this size?
小さい？
Is it too small?
Tiny
真ん丸でいいの？
More circular?
大丈夫　ゆでると
少し膨らむから ちょうどいいよ
Don't worry.
They'll expand a bit when we boil them, so that's perfect.
大きめの白玉のときは—
When making large rice flour dumplings,
you would put a little dent in them like this,
少し こんなふうに
おへそをつけるんだけど
今回は小粒だから
but today we're making smaller ones.
Next we put them in boiling water.
（あかり）そして
これを沸騰したお湯に入れて—
After two or three minutes,
they'll come burbling up to the surface.
２〜３分すると
ポコポコ浮いてくるから
（あかり）もうちょっとかな
（ひなた）もうちょっと？
Maybe a little more.
A little more?
（あかり）
そこから更に１分くらい ゆでて…
Then you keep them in the
boiling water for another minute.
氷水に入れて キュッと身を締める
Next, transfer them to ice water, which firms them up.
And...
…で はい 出来上がり！
Ta-da!
they're done!
Voila!
ご覧あれ！
Springy
Th-That was so fast! And simple!
は… はやっ！　簡単だよ！
Wonderful
Wonderful!
ハァ〜ッ…
（あかり）
まあまあ 最初はラフに砂糖醤油(さとうじょうゆ)で
At first, let's just try it with sugar and soy sauce.
Yum!
It's so chewy!
モキュモキュしてる！
（あかり）白玉自体は
まあ これでクリアとして—
The rice flour dumplings pass the taste test,
but the challenge is the syrup.
シロップよね 問題は
Powdered green tea is best, right?
Or plum syrup, or chilled sweet red bean soup...
抹茶でしょう
梅シロップに 冷やし汁粉…
ン〜ッ…　やっぱり 抹茶おいしい
It's so delicious with powdered green tea!
But powdered green tea is expensive.
でも 高いのよね お抹茶
I want to make each cup cost less than 300 yen.
１杯３００円以上には
したくないし う〜ん…
（ひなた）えっと
白玉粉２００グラムで
Um, if we can get about 60 small dumplings from 200 grams of rice flour...
小さめの白玉が—
大体60コくらい
取れるとして…
え〜っと…
Let's see...
Hmm
Oh!
I got it!
そうだ！
じゃ 冷たいミルクティーは？
How about cold milk tea?
It's rich and sweet!
こってりと甘いの！
ハッ…　いいかも
That could be good!
確かに 紅茶の茶葉のほうが
ずっと安いかも
True, black tea leaves would be much cheaper!
ハッ…　じゃ いっそ—
Why don't we also put in black pearl tapioca?
ブラックパールタピオカも
入れちゃおっか
色のアクセントにもなるし
It would make nice color accents!
（ひなた）いい！　それいい！
（モモ）ハッ…
That's a great idea!
To defray the cost of the tapioca,
タピオカにお金かかる分 器と
スプーンは使い捨てのじゃなくて
instead of using disposable bowls and spoons,
we can gather spoons and bowls from our house, Crescent Moon, and Aunt Misaki's pub,
家(うち)のと三日月堂のと
美咲(みさき)おばさまのお店のをかき集めて
and just keep washing them,
even though it might be a hassle.
どんどん洗って回しましょう
ちょっと大変だけど…
Oh, we can have Kiriyama do the washing!
（ひなた）そうだ！
桐山(きりやま)君に洗ってもらおうよ
What? Wait, what? Huh?!
（零(れい)）えっ？
（あかり）名案！　お願いしよう！
Good idea! Let's ask him!
（相米二(そめじ)）うん
だんごは まあまあ よくできてるな
You did a pretty good job with the dumplings.
You put them in ice water to firm them up, right?
ちゃんと氷水で締めてあるな うん
And tapioca?
…で タピオカね
フッ…　またハイカラな物(もん)を
Another fancy thing, huh?
えらい歯応えがいいもんだな
デンプンの一種だよな？　これは
Hey, it's pretty firm.
This is a type of starch, right?
（ひなた）おじいちゃん…
（あかり）ど… どうかな？
Grandpa.
Wh-What do you think?
Thump
う〜ん…　まあ いいだろう
Well, I guess it'll do.
Damn, it's actually really good.
ちきしょう　うまいな…
（相米二）
若い者(もん)が好きそうな気がする
I got a feeling the youngsters will really like them.
It should sell pretty well at a food stand.
屋台でパ〜ッと売るにはいいだろう
お祭りだしな
It's a festival, after all.
Beaming
（２人）わあ…　やった！
（はしゃぎ声）
Beaming
Yay!
This one was especially good.
（相米二）特に これが良かったな
梅シロップか？
Plum syrup?
（相米二）さっぱりしてて味がいい
（ひなた）あっ…
It's refreshing and tasty.
これは ちほちゃんが
作ってくれた梅シロップなんだ
That plum syrup was made by Chiho.
うん？　そうかい
Yeah?
That's a nice smell from the plums.
いい梅の香りだ
（ひなた）夏休みに入って すぐ…
As soon as summer vacation started,
ちほちゃんに会いに行きました
we went to see Chiho.
Chiho!
ちほちゃ〜ん！
Hina.
（ちほ）ひなちゃん…
（ひなた）
牧場を案内してもらったり…
She took me around the farm.
Wag
Wahh
Love!
（子犬）しゅき〜
（子犬）遊んで　わふわふ
Play with me. Woof, woof!
Let's play!
（子犬）遊んで〜
She showed me Hana and her puppies.
（ひなた）
犬のハナちゃんの子犬たちを
見せてもらったりしました
（ハナちゃん）好き〜 好き〜
Love! I love you!
（ひなた）話している途中—
Sometimes when we talked,
ちほちゃんは 時々 黙って—
Chiho would go silent and space out.
ボ〜ッとしていました
佐藤(さとう)先生のお話だと
ちほちゃんは今でも—
Ms. Satou said that even now,
Chiho freezes up when she sees a girl around junior-high age.
中学生くらいの女の子を見ると
動けなくなってしまうのだそうです
同い年くらいの子を見ると—
Seeing someone of the same age makes all of her painful memories come flooding back into her heart and mind.
苦しかったことや
つらかったことが—
ものすごい勢いで 胸と頭に
いっぱいに あふれてしまう
それに体が 一生懸命
抵抗しているのだそうです
Apparently her body is resisting that with all her strength.
それを
少しずつ 前と同じように—
But Chiho is working hard here, so that little by little,
話したり
行動したりできるように—
ちほちゃんは 少しずつ
ここで頑張っているのだと—
she'll be able to talk and act like she used to.
That's what Ms. Satou told me.
先生は話してくれました
Chiho
夕方 ちほちゃんは熱を出し—
Chiho developed a fever in the evening,
彼女のお母さんが
車で駅まで送ってくれました
so her mom dropped us off at the station.
“ちほの味方でいてくれて
本当に本当に ありがとう”
"Thank you so much for supporting Chiho."
Her mom said that as she clasped my hands.
…と お母さんは
何度も私の手を握ってくれました
“ここで
ちほと一緒に頑張ります”と
She said, "Chiho and I will be doing our best here."
まず最初は
動物のお友達を作ること
You start by making friends with animals.
After that, you make friends with people who are older than you.
次は 年が上のお友達を
ステップの３つ目は
年の近い友達を作ること
And step three is making friends with someone who's close to your own age.
ちほちゃんは—
Even now,
今も闘っているのだ
Chiho is fighting.
ちほちゃんに夏祭りの写真を送ろう
I'll send her photos from the summer festival.
梅シロップを みんなが
おいしそうに食べてる写真を
Photos of everyone enjoying the plum syrup.
そして また彼女に—
And then,
I'll go
会いに行くんだ
visit her again.
（ひなた）さ〜て 行きますか
（あかり）始めましょうかね
All right, shall we go?
Let's get started.
（あかり）いらっしゃいませ！
三日月堂で〜す！
Welcome!
We're Crescent Moon!
Crescent Moon
How about some sweet,
chilled rice flour dumplings with syrup?
（ひなた）冷たくて甘〜い
冷やし白玉シロップいかがですか？
Sweet and cold rice flour dumplings with syrup!
甘くて冷たい白玉シロップ！
よく冷えてますよ！
It's nice and cold!
Here's your plum syrup.
梅シロップ お待たせしました
Thank you.
（女性）ありがとう
It looks really good.
おいしそう！
お皿 新しいの出します
Here's some clean plates.
（零）こっち下げますね
（あかり）ありがとう 桐山君
And I'll take these back.
Thank you, Kiriyama!
Prompt
Also 100 yen coins.
あと 百円玉 ２本ほぐして
ここ入れときます
Prompt
I'll empty two rolls in here for change.
And dish cloths.
それと ふきん
洗ったの こっちにかけます
Prompt
I'll hang up the ones I washed here.
（あかり）
桐山君 最高！　なんて気がつくの
Kiriyama is the best!
Prompt
He's so considerate!
Wow! That's a big help!
（ひなた）すごい！　助かる！
Prompt
Sorry for working you so hard, kid.
悪いな 坊主 こき使って
Here. At least have a cool ginger drink.
まあ 冷やし飴(あめ)でも飲みな
ありがとうございます
Thank you.
There are so many people here.
すごいですね お客さん
ハァ〜ッ…　おいしい
This is good.
The festival is a success.
大盛況だな
つられて こっちまで よく売れる
And we're selling like crazy too.
This is my first time doing something like this,
僕 こういうの初めてなんで
なんか…
so I'm kind of surprised by how fun it is.
びっくりです　楽しくて
（ひなた）桐山君！　桐山君！
Kiriyama!
（ひなた）ちょっと…
（零）うん？　どうしたの？
Hey...
What's up?
Yo. How you doing?
（高橋(たかはし)）チ〜ッス　どうも
（零）あっ 高橋君
Takahashi.
あれ？
また すごく大きくなってない？
Huh?
Have you gotten way taller again?
Chiho made this plum syrup.
これ
ちほちゃんが作った梅シロップなの
（高橋）どうも
Thanks.
He's huge.
（零）でっかいな…
Whoa
（相米二）
うん…　ばあさん 美香子(みかこ)
Grandma.
Mikako.
（美香子）
おいしい三色だんごですよ
いかがですか？
Delicious three-colored rice flour dumplings here!
Would you like any?
（彩(さい)）いらっしゃいませ
Welcome!
It's all right.
（相米二）大丈夫だぞ
They're doing a great job.
あいつらは立派にやっている
It's a nice night.
いい夜だね
零ちゃん
Rei.
私…
This...
こういうのがいいな
is what I like.
こういうのが大好きみたい
I guess I love this kind of thing.
Yeah.
Ka-ching
Stuffed
Tremble
Wow!
すごい…　まだ７時前なのに
あっという間に こんなに…
Tremble
It isn't even 7 o'clock yet.
We made all this in no time at all!
Tremble
い… 今なら お台所の晩ご飯用に
作っておいたカレーだって—
A-At this rate, I think we can easily sell the curry that's on the stove for dinner tonight!
飛ぶように売れるんじゃないかしら
C-Calm down, Sis!
お… お姉ちゃん　落ち着いて！
Curry is no good!
カレー ダメ！
ウチ 和菓子屋だってば！
We're a sweets shop!
大変 お姉ちゃん！
Oh no, Sis!
We're down to less than one box of dumplings!
白玉 もう１パックしかない！
あんなに作ったのに
And we made so many...
ゆでましょう 今すぐに！
ムハ〜ッ…
Let's boil some more right away!
We can't!
ムリ　だって
もうシロップが　アア…
We're out of syrup too!
Empty
What?
なんてこと　せっかくの
稼ぎ時だというのに…
Right when we're on a selling streak?
Fwip
Empty
Idiots!
バッカ野郎！
きな粉と黒蜜があるじゃない
Crackle
We still have soybean flour and brown sugar syrup, right?
G-Grandpa!
（ひなた･あかり）
お… おじいちゃん！
Akari, boil some water!
（相米二）あかり　湯を沸かせ！
（あかり）はい！
Right!
Hina, mind the store!
（相米二）ひなは ここを頼む
（ひなた）うん！
Okay!
Kid, buy us some ice.
おう 坊主！　氷を買ってきてくれ
高橋のせがれに聞けば分かる
Ask the Takahashi boy and he'll tell you where.
（零）あっ はい！
O-Okay!
I'll knead the dumplings!
（相米二）俺は だんごを練る
All right!
（あかり）よ〜し　川本(かわもと)家…
Let's do this, Kawamoto family!
（あかり）ファイッ！
（一同）オーッ！
Yeah!
Being Here
Summer Vacation (Part 1)
The March City Festival was so much fun.
（ひなた）
楽しかったなぁ 三月町(さんがつちょう)祭り
Cozy
We should've prepared more syrup, huh?
シロップ
もっと用意しとけばよかったね
I never thought we'd sell out by 7 o'clock.
まさか７時台に完売しちゃうなんて
もったいなかった
Such a shame.
Speaking of shame, you spent too much on it and were too generous with the portions.
…ていうか お前ら
原価かけすぎ　サービスしすぎ
After working so hard drenched in sweat,
this is our net profit.
あんなに汗まみれになって
純利益が これじゃ—
This is what they call "going through great pains in vain"!
骨折り損の
くたびれ儲(もう)けってやつだぞ
だが…
But...
it really gets my blood pumping when we're swarmed with customers.
客が あんなにも
わんさか押し寄せるってのは—
やっぱり血が躍るなぁ
Yeah
Thanks to all the people who stopped by, we sold lots of our usual sweets too.
人が たくさん来てくれたおかげで
定番の菓子も よく売れた
I guess a loss leader is fine when
it comes to attracting customers.
やっぱ
客寄せになる目玉商品は でかいな
It's like when you go to the supermarket if they have milk on sale for 128 yen, right?
スーパーでも “牛乳１パック
128円”とか言ったら—
行っちゃうものね
モモ肉100グラム68円とか
トマト缶１コ78円とか
Or 100 grams of ham for 68 yen, or a can of tomatoes for 78 yen.
But of course you buy other stuff while you're there, right?
…で ほかの物も
もちろん買ってしまうのよね
お前らの母さんも ばあちゃんも
なかなかの商売上手だったっけなぁ
Your mom and grandma were both natural saleswomen.
甘い物から しょっぱい物まで
いろんな物こさえては—
Whether they'd make something sweet or sour, it didn't matter.
There'd always be a line of people.
いっつも行列作ってた
It was really something.
大したもんだと
祭りのたんびに思ってた
I thought that every time there was a festival.
（ひなた）あっ…
（相米二）お前らにも見せたかった
I wish you girls would've seen it too.
わあ…
Glow
私 覚えてる
にゃんこ焼きに ぼんぼり焼き
I remember.
The deep-fried kitty-cats and lanterns.
The bags with the huge ribbons were so cute.
でっかいリボンの袋
かわいかったな
（あかり）“お金かけずに
手間かけて”って よく言ってた
They often said, "Spend effort, not money."
私も袋詰め手伝ったな
I'd help out by stuffing the bags.
すごく楽しかった
It was so much fun.
You did a great job for your first time out there.
（相米二）お前たちも最初にしては
なかなかに立派だったぞ
But you still need to work on sales,
and you have a ways to go with finesse and insight.
売り上げとかは もちろん
手際も読みも まだまだだが
来年も またやってみてもいいぞ
But you can give it another shot next year, if you want.
What?!
ホント？　いいの？
Really?! Is it okay?!
I'll do my best!
F
w
頑張る！
F
w
o
F
w
o
F
w
o
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
I'll have customers lined up,
just like Mom and Grandma did!
私も おばあちゃんと
お母さんみたいに 行列を作る！
O
h
I-I need to think about the menu right away!
O
h
さ… 早速
メニューを考えなくっちゃ！
O
h
Stretch
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
F
w
o
h
Grab
Hina! Calm down.
ひな　落ち着いて
Grab
…ていうか まず受験
志望校 どうするの？
You have entrance exams first.
Which schools are you applying to?
あっ そうか！　そうだった…
Oh yeah!
That's right!
（あかり）あした 夏期テストで
夏休みだけど登校日でしょう
You have a test tomorrow.
Despite being summer vacation, it's a school day.
範囲は ちゃんと勉強したの？
Did you make sure to study?
う… うん したよ
あと少し残ってるけど…
Uh, yeah, I did.
I still have to study a little more, though.
あっ そうだ！　お姉ちゃん
ゼリーは どうだろう？
I've got it!
Sis, how about jelly?!
Hey!
（相米二）手ぇ止まってる！
Your hands have stopped moving!
Wrap them already!
チャッチャと包んで！
どら焼き乾いちまうぞ
The red bean pancakes will dry out!
R-Right!
（ひなた）は… はい！
おじいちゃん ごめんなさい！
Sorry, Grandpa!
I can't!
（小見川(こみがわ)）
ムリ…　ぼ… ぼぼ… 僕 ムリです
I-I-I can't do it!
Tremble
Shiver
絶対ムリですってば…
Tremble
Shiver
I just can't do it!
Tremble
Shiver
ムリ…
３Ａの担任なんて ムリ ムリ！
It's impossible! I can't be the homeroom teacher for 3A!
（国分(こくぶ)）あ〜 大丈夫 大丈夫
It'll be fine. Don't worry.
…多分
Maybe.
I'll be here if you need me.
（国分）俺も 一応 ついているし
（小見川）荷が重すぎますよ…
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
i
n
c
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
It's too much to bear!
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
You saw the menacing look of Takagi's mother too!
P
a
n
i
c
見たでしょう？
あの高城(たかぎ)の親の剣幕(けんまく)
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
P
a
n
i
c
ぼ… 僕
絶対 渡り合う自信ないッスよ
I-I don't have the confidence to contend with her!
What? What?!
新しい担任って…
A new homeroom teacher?!
You're entrusting the precious last trimester of junior high to a young teacher like that?!
こんな若い人に大事な中３の後期を
任せるというんですか？
What is the school thinking?!
学校側は何を考えてらっしゃるの？
Wahhh
ヒイーッ！　ムリです
僕 まだ新人なんですよ
Wahhh
I can't do it! I'm still a newbie!
You may be a newbie, but I'm an old man!
お前が新人なら 俺は老人だ！
Not to mention, I can't physically be
the homeroom teacher for two classes!
…つうか ２クラス担任なんて
物理的に完全にアウトだっつうの！
I can't watch 90 students by myself!
１人で90人見られるわけなかろう！
On top of that, I've got my duties as the head teacher!
しかも俺は
学年主任の仕事もあんだよ
それに この高城との話し合い
いつまで続けるんですか？
Besides, how long will this ongoing discussion with Takagi last?
言ったろう
I told you.
Getting her to understand what she did is part of the job.
何をしたのか分からせるのも
仕事のうちだ
（小見川）お言葉ですが…
With all due respect, no matter what
else we say to her, it won't do any good.
これ以上
彼女に何を語りかけてもムダですよ
She's already decided not to feel any guilt over it.
彼女は 罪の意識そのものを—
“理解するまい”って
決めちゃってるんですから
Why do we have to spend all this time on it?
なんで ここまで手をかけて
やらないといけないんです？
It doesn't make sense.
おかしいですよ
迷惑をかけた人間のほうが—
Paying all this attention to the
person who caused the trouble,
こんなに手厚く
かまってもらえるなんて
while the victim, Sakura Chiho,
not only moved away because of it,
やられた佐倉(さくら)ちほは
転校までしたうえに—
but she isn't going to school over there yet.
向こうでも まだ
学校にも通えていないんですよ
（小見川）ひゃ… 百歩譲って
本当に悪意がなかったんだとしても
I-If she's unwilling to give in, even if there was no malice...
I mean, after taking it this far,
…ていうか
もう ここまでやったんなら—
it doesn't matter if there was ill will or not!
もう悪意なんて あったって
なくったって同じですよ！
小見川…
Komigawa.
I'll write it on her record.
僕は書きますよ 内申書に…
新担任として
ホントのこと 洗いざらい
As her new homeroom teacher,
I'll write it all down.
“独善的で
他人に対する攻撃性が強い”
That she thinks she's always right and
is very aggressive toward other people.
“グループの
リーダー的な存在であり—”
That she's like the leader of the group,
but she causes major problems in class.
“クラス内部で
大規模な問題を起こした”
…て！
And...
when somebody causes a problem,
they need to take responsibility for it!
自分が引き起こしたことについて
人は 責任を持たねばならない
僕は そう思う
報いは受けるべきです
That's what I believe.
There must be punishment.
Otherwise...
でないと…
it's just wrong, isn't it?
おかしいでしょう！
（高城）ねえ 先生
Hey, Mr. Kokubu.
（高城）答え出た？
Do you have an answer?
全員が頑張ったり—
Did you find a reason for why everyone has to put in some effort
努力したりしなくちゃ
いけないっていう理由
探してくれた？
and do their best?
ああ　あれから いろいろ考えた
Well, I've been thinking a lot since it came up.
でな…
And...
I couldn't find an answer.
見つからんかった
Huh?
“見つからなかった”って—
You didn't find one?
なに？　それ
What the heck?
Attendance Records
（国分）さんざ頭を絞ってみたが
I racked my brains,
but in the end, if I'm being honest, I came up blank.
いざ考えてみると
正直 １コも出てこなかった
不思議なもんだよな
It's strange, isn't it?
そういや 考えてみたら—
And when I thought about it,
I realized I never even had any doubts.
俺は そこに
疑問を持ったことすらなかった
なんでだったんだろうな…
Why was that?
努力は しんどいが—
It's hard to make an effort,
but I always assumed people had to do it.
しなきゃいかんとしか
思ってこんかった
そうこうしているうちに—
All this time I thought making an effort
was something you do for your own sake.
“努力は 自分のために
するものだ”っていう…
もう誰に言われたんだか—
Anyway, I'd been told that often enough that I don't even remember who first said it or where I'd read that idea.
何で読んだんだか
覚えてないくらい—
耳タコの このフレーズに
ぶち当たってな
この年になって やっと—
Now that I've reached this age,
“ああ このセリフ
本当なんだ”って—
I felt that phrase was true from the bottom of my heart.
心から思ったよ
For the longest time, I probably just...
きっと俺は ただ ずっと…
今よりマシな人間ってのに
なりたかっただけだったんだな
wanted to become a better person than I was back then.
I see.
急に自分語りとかですか？
So we're suddenly talking about you?
Is it going to take long?
長くなっちゃいます？
No.
ならんよ
Attendance Records
タイムアップだ
Time's up.
今日で
お前のクラスの臨時担任は終わりだ
This was my last day as your class's interim homeroom teacher.
なあ 高城
Hey, Takagi.
Right now, I think you have so much
anxiety that you don't know what to do.
お前は多分 今
不安で不安でしょうがないんだな
何もやったことがないから
まだ自分の大きさすら分からねえ
You haven't done anything in your life yet, so you don't know your own capabilities.
不安の原因は そこだ
That's the source of your anxiety.
Mr. Kokubu.
先生？
（国分）
お前が何にも頑張れないのは—
You refuse to make an effort with anything
自分の大きさを知って
がっかりするのが怖いからだ
because you're scared of learning your own capacity and being disappointed by it.
だが 高城
がっかりしても大丈夫だ
But, Takagi,
it's okay to be disappointed.
Once you learn your own capacity,
you at last understand what it is you should do.
自分の大きさが分かったら
何をしたらいいかが やっと分かる
When you understand yourself,
自分のことが分かってくれば—
やりたいことも
だんだん ぼんやり見えてくる
what you want to do will also become more clear.
そうすれば 今の その
ものすご〜い不安からだけは—
Once you do that, you'll at least be able to get past your incredible anxiety.
抜け出ることができるよ
それだけは—
I can guarantee
俺が保証する
at least that.
（ひなた）
テストが終わったその夜に
私は いっぱい絵を描いた
After I was done with the test,
that night, I made a lot of drawings.
頭の中に
きれいな色のお菓子が—
There were so many colorful sweets that
wouldn't stop swimming around in my head.
あふれて あふれて 止まらなかった
Hina, how long are you going to stay up?
（あかり）
ひな！　いつまで起きてるの？
Take your bath.
早くお風呂入って
Hey, don't just leave the fan on.
ちょっと 扇風機つけっぱなしで…
風邪ひくってば もう
Sheesh, you'll catch a cold.
Oh, Hina.
ひなったら…
もう 何をこんなに…
Jeez. What is all this?
Jeez...
もう…　なに？　これ
What is this?
フフッ…　かわいい
It's cute.
全部 すっごくおいしそう
They all look delicious.
うん すごくいい！
ワクワクしちゃう！
Yeah.
These are great.
I'm getting excited!
Summer Vacation (Part 1)
Surrounded by a landscape on the verge of permanent stasis
I found myself searching for something
I took up a mask to make my pitifully weak self appear stable
And donned it boldly
The sound of my frozen footsteps as I walked along the river
Was easily overpowered by the roar of a passing train
Yet I kept chanting "I just gotta take another step" to myself
Over and over again
Can you hear me proclaiming that I'm standing right here?
Even in bare feet I can go wherever the hell I want
I don't know where I might find myself at the end
I can't begin to guess, but I can just ink in
A new landscape to suit me as I go
Next Episode Preview
Episode 42
（零）すごくきれいで
おいしそうだ
They're so beautiful and look delicious.
Rei, how old were you when you first wanted to be a pro shogi player?
（ひなた）零ちゃんは
何歳のころ—
プロ棋士になりたいって
思ったの？
Kiriyama!
（樋口(ひぐち)）桐山君！
いやぁ 晴れましたなぁ
It's a nice and clear day, is it not?
（モモ）
モモ つるつる大好き！
ムハ〜ッ！
I love slippery food!
（林田(はやしだ)）ホントに
かわいいじゃないか
She really is cute!
Illustration: Akiman
（あかり）おじいちゃん
ひなの考えたお菓子見て
Grandpa, look at the sweets Hina thought up!
（相米二）
むっ！　こりゃいいな！
These are incredible!